if you've been following my work for a
while you know that I bring together
insights from many different fields to
help us understand how change happens in
the world and one of the major thrusts
of the study that I've done over the
last several years has been to bring
insights from cognitive science together
so that we could tackle issues in
politics economic development social
innovation collaboration organizational
development in several other fields and
I know many of you out there are
grappling with how to bring these this
vast body of knowledge together in your
own work so what I want to do today is I
want to share with you a broad set of
books that I have read that have been
very helpful to me in shaping my
thinking and that I think could be
helpful to you so you can kind of think
of this is like a crash course in the
applications of cognitive science to
large-scale social change so let's start
out with some books more in the
philosophical space so first of all I've
got this one right here in mind where by
Andy Clark this is the subtitles in
introduction to the philosophy of
cognitive science and this book is a
great overview of the major
philosophical battles and debates in the
cognitive sciences throughout the last
century so it's kind of a must read for
anyone who really wants to understand
the landscape of of science and a
philosophy around our understanding of
human nature now another one that's more
recent this one right here by Jerome
Feldman from molecule to metaphor is a
book that explores how the brain is able
to construct conceptual architecture to
hold our thoughts so this is a book that
lays out how how the workings of the
brain are related to the functioning of
language it's really an incredible piece
of work but maybe a bit scholarly for
you now this one here george leigh
coughs women fire and dangerous things
is one of his most important books most
people know like offers work in politics
but this book is actually it does
something pretty spectacular but
something that might sound a little
academic what he does is he describes
how what's been learned in neuroscience
and in psychology and in my areas of
perceptual research like say the way
that our visual system works those kinds
of fields to help us understand human
conceptualization and just in case
you're wondering the title of women
firing dangerous things is actually a
category in an indigenous tribal culture
where one category like the category for
blueness there's a category that codes
women fire aren't dangerous things and
this book explains how categories work
in the human mind now you've probably
heard people talking about or seen in my
writings that there's a growing
understanding that the way the mind
works is grounded in the body well this
book by Joseph LeDoux is a
neuroscientist it's called the synaptic
self how our brains become what we are
explains how I kind of in a lot of depth
a lot of detail the particular workings
of the brain and now those workings of
the brain lead to the processing of
emotions and thoughts so it's a quite an
accomplishment as well and they did
links our sense of identity and our
ability to conceive of ourselves as
cogent whole autonomous beings through
the workings of our brains in a similar
brain actually similar vein I want to
share with you three books written by
another neuroscientist named Antonio
Damasio so the first one day cards error
is kind of a classic now in the
cognitive sciences it's published in the
early 90s and this book explains in
through a lot of case studies of people
experiencing degenerative brain disease
and head trauma it shows how how
reasoning requires the working of
emotion and it's really a wonderful book
and is widely cited one that's less
known but i think is possibly even more
significant as the second book in his
series the feeling of what happens this
book gives the first fully neurological
account of how consciousness can arise
in the workings of the brain and so if
you're interested in understanding how
the mind can come from the way the brain
works this is a must-read now it is a
bit dense at times and it deals with a
lot of neuroscience so you have to
grapple with that but if you want to
understand how consciousness works in a
scientifically rigorous way this is
probably the best entry point you're
going to find and then he capped off his
series Damacio did with this book here
looking for Spinoza joy sorrow in the
feeling brain this is much more of a
philosophical book so the great thing
about Antonio is that he's a one of
those various philosophically astute
scientists so he knows philosophy as
well as you know science and what he
does in this book is he goes back into
the era of later enlightenment
philosophy and looks at the work of
Spinoza and was a lesser known
philosopher and shows that Spinoza was
basically right about the minded human
nature and the origins of morality but
his work was largely overlooked because
neuroscience wasn't advanced enough and
it wasn't until the late 20th century
the neuroscience came what was able to
catch up with his thinking now another
philosopher who you may have heard of if
you follow the work of George leg off it
is a collaborator of George's is a guy
named Mark Johnson so here's a book
moral imagination implications of
cognitive science ethics see Mark
Johnson in this book this is a really
fun read and it's very insightful about
how human creativity works and how we're
able to blend concepts and create new
understandings from found a kind of
grounded structures of thought like
metaphors that map our bodily experience
to the conceptual domain and then he
elaborates from those basic sorts of
things to a full explanation of how
we're able to imagine scenarios to test
out the ethics of those situations and
he gives us the first account of
body based situational ethics he came
back about or was it 15 years later and
did a follow a book of the meaning of
the body is the aesthetics of human
understanding and this book is just a
real pleasure to read if you're
interested in the implications of
cognitive science for the study of
culture the arts music ethics then this
is your book it's very readable and like
one of the things he does is he explains
how music theory is related to the part
of the brain that what's called the
sensorimotor cortex that explains how
our ability to simulate motion like see
a coordinated activity of the hand or
the leg is actually activated and used
in the experience of melody and tempo
and music so this is a really cool book
to look at the relationship between the
arts and science through a philosophy of
embodied cognitive science more
generally this idea of embodiment is a
something that's come about in many
different fields and I'm really pleased
that Raymond Gibbs who's a cognitive
psychologist put together this book
embodiment in cognitive science now this
is definitely more of a researchers book
than a laypersons book because what ray
does in this book is he goes through and
systematically gathers up all the
peer-reviewed research of different
different experimental studies that show
how embodiment works so he looked you
know he gathers up information and
robotics and artificial intelligence he
grabbed gathers information in physical
therapy where people will have say their
arm has been cut off because of a car
accident and they're given a limb like
you know prosthetic limb and then he'll
look at how the brain has this kind of
ghost LEM effect and there's a lot of
different studies that show that so he
goes through and systematically gathers
up all the research that validates
embodiment through I don't know 20 25
different fields more of a scholarly
book definitely for the researcher but
if you're interested in
understanding our body Matt works and
seeing the full evidence for it this is
a fantastic resource now if you want to
think more about embodiment at a
philosophical level this is another one
of those bounding texts it's widely
cited now the embodiment in its by
Francisco Varela Evan Thompson and
Eleanor rush as a neuroscientist a
philosopher and a cognitive psychologist
and what they do in this book that's
really beautiful is they critique faulty
philosophies of cognitive science
through the lens of Buddhist
contemplative practice which might sound
like that's a non sequitur like it
doesn't really fit but as it turns out
the introspective approach of presence
of being aware of how the mind is
working in the body that kind of
mindfulness meditation gives us insights
into how we've developed a flawed notion
of separation between mind and body and
what are actually false notions of self
and so Buddhist contemplative practice
has come upon insights that modern or
contemporary psychology and neuroscience
are now validating and this book is a
great entry point into the philosophy of
embodied mind and it's now widely cited
for that purpose now another one that
you know I said that there's George Lake
off him you know from his work in
politics you may not know that he wrote
a book with Rafael Nunez called where
mathematics comes from in this book I it
lays out how the the concepts used in
mathematics are actually grounded in our
physical neurological and psychological
being so the way that our brains process
information and the way that we
cultivate knowledge through our
experience is also how we learn
mathematics and so this book offers the
beginnings of a philosophy of
mathematics to show that something that
seemingly so abstract is also grounded
in the bodily experience of course
probably the most important work that
George Lake office has created and he
wrote it with Mark Johnson is this book
philosophy in the flesh the embodied
mind in its challenge to Western thought
now it took them seven years to write
this book and you can see it's thick
right this is a big one this is the tome
you could maybe even think of the
as george leigh coughs magnum opus mrs.
has his primary or most important
accomplishment in this book what George
and Mark do is they systematically go
through the major tenets of Western
philosophy and re craft them based on
what we now know about cognitive science
so they take 2,500 years of philosophy
and they recast it with what we now know
from science this is a major
accomplishment this is one of those
books that I think is going to have
ripples across the scholarly community
for decades and it's still not widely
read enough I mean in a few circles it's
well known but for the most part people
haven't heard of this book they're much
more familiar with George's political
works speaking of which if I were to
bring out George's works is most popular
one of course is this one don't think of
an elephant this is a collection of
essays that apply cognitive science and
specifically framing and metaphor to a
political discourse and you've probably
heard of that one what you may or may
not know is that that book was actually
inspired or it's kind of a condensing of
a much larger book moral politics how
liberals and conservatives think which
he originally published in 1996 and then
a second edition came out in 2002 this
is the book that explains how the nation
is family metaphor Maps systematically
onto moral world views that are very
different for program for liberals and
for conservatives so if you want to
understand political thought this book
lays it out and what is it it's more
than 500 450 pages so this is a very
thorough exploration of human conceptual
thought and moral reasoning within the
political domain now George came out
later with another book the political
mind this book does a lot more of a kind
of overview and synthesis of how
cognitive science maps onto political
thought and behavior so if you're
interested in political thought and
behavior this is a very important book
and kind of a partner to it written by
another researcher drew westen is this
book the political brain
now see drew westen is a
neuropsychologist so he's a psychologist
who studies the information processing
in the brain he's at Emory University
and in this book he explains a lot of
how brain function works and how it
relates to political decision-making so
it's a pretty well-known in political
circles these days but definitely a good
one if you want to understand cognitive
science as its applied to politics now
George has written a couple of other
books that you may also be familiar
familiar with this one thinking points
what she wrote in partnership with the
intellectual staff at the Rockbridge
Institute this is much more of a
practitioners book so if you're
interested in advocacy political
communications engagement strategy
community organizing this is a good book
to read because it's definitely written
with the practitioner in mind not nearly
as scholarly as some of these other
books now George also kind of following
that book I mentioned earlier women find
dangerous things George created this
book I wrote this book whose freedom the
battle over America's most important
idea and this book looks at how the
conceptual structure or the category
structure for freedom works now that
might seem like it's an intellectual or
a kind of academic endeavor but it turns
out that freedom is a fundamentally
contested concept which means that the
context you bring to it and the values
you bring to it shape what it means to
you when George does in this book is he
rigorously and comprehensively
deconstructs the category of freedom to
show how different political world views
shape how it's understood so that's
that's an important one for political
thinking now this book here what word
well didn't know this is actually a
collection of writings and you can see
propaganda and the new face of American
politics so this book was written on the
anniversary it was the 50th anniversary
of the publication of an essay that
Orwell wrote about politics in the
English language and
the editors of the book went out and
asked to set a large number of thinkers
to reflect on what Orwell got right and
what we've learned since then this is
not the one of those practical books for
political communication so now I'm
moving a little bit into another space
you're probably familiar with a george
leigh coughs work on framing we may not
know is that framing actually has been
developed in several different fields
and one of the other foundational
thinkers of framing is this guy Erving
Goffman so golf Minh wrote this book
frame analysis in the mid-70s and he's a
sociologist so he wrote this book from
the perspective of how do we understand
social context and what are the roles
and relationships in those social
contexts and how do they send our
expectations so if you want to
understand more about framing then this
is a really good book for you to read to
get a deeper understanding of where it
comes from and how it applies to social
process a more recent book in framing is
this one framing public life so it's a
delayed by a stephen race oscar gandy
and august grant and this book is much
more about media and communications this
is a collection of essays that look at
how frame analysis is done in media and
discourse so if you want to do frame
analysis and discourse this is a very
good book to have now in other domains
or we could think about cognitive
science you know there's as you're
seeing already there's a lot here but
like let's take let's let's look at
religion and morality so there's this
great book the spell of the sensuous by
David Abram this is more of a
philosophical book but what he does in
this book is he explores how our moral
sensibility in the modern world has
become separated from nature and he's a
cognitive psychologist as well as
cultural anthropologist so he studies
indigenous tribal cultures to show how
the the evolution of language in
different cultures led to a place where
we ended up having what are called
written phonetic languages and those
languages have characters that represent
sounds in the mouth rather than things
that are in nature and that created an
abstraction or a separation of mind and
thought from nature so this book gives
us a sense of the origins of mind-body
dualism how it comes about through a way
of structuring language and now that
plays out in morality and our
sensibilities about the natural world
now another one another one of those
kind of key books to interested in the
applications of cognitive science to
religion is this one religion explained
by Pascal boy yay you see the title of
the subtitle is the evolutionary origins
of religious thought so Pascal boy a
brings cognitive science and
ethnographic field research from
anthropology it brings them together and
explains how religious concepts get
transferred from one generation to the
next so if you're interested in how
religion works anthropologically this is
a great book for you kind of a partner
to that one is this other book this is
more of an academic book modes of
religiosity by Harvey White House and
this book as he calls it a cognitive
theory of religious transmission this is
more of a technical dive into Pascal
boys theory of how concepts or conveyed
across generations so you could think if
you're familiar with meme theory how a
meme is spread across society this book
looks at the cognitive psychology of
that and so that's another one you're
interested in religious thought and
cognitive science now there are two
books here one of them is the moral mind
by mark Hauser that there was a moral
animal by Robert right these are both
more what would be called evolutionary
psychology books and actually I when I
read them I found there are a couple of
problems with them philosophically you
could address and that large pile of
books I shared with you on on philosophy
but they're still really good at helping
you understand how evolutionary biology
can inform the way we understand human
nature and morality
in that same vein here's one of those
books it has more of a light title but
is actually very very insightful is why
sex is fun the evolution of human
sexuality by Jared Diamond you might
know Jared Diamond because of his book
Guns Germs and Steel or the other one he
wrote collapse this book which is a lot
shorter looks at how we can understand
human sexuality by looking at the
history of hominids meaning I looking at
primates how are we similar to or
different from bonobos how are we
similar to our different from gorillas
and really bringing a strong
evolutionary biology perspective to
sexuality and immorality it's a fun read
but it's also very very insightful now
while we're talking about evolution here
are two books for you that give a much
deeper context to our human nature works
so here's one on deep history in the
brain by Daniel Lords mail this book is
actually written what the goal of
changing the way that people study
history but it's really a wonderful book
in that it shows if we want to
understand human history in our deep
origins which means how do we arise from
evolution how did we come into being
with the changing planet and that deep
historic sensibility then we have to
understand how the brain evolved we have
to understand how the the core kind of
hind brain or the brainstem part of our
brain is related to reptiles for example
and now the evolution of reptiles shaped
the way that they behave that also
partly shapes how we behave so this book
is really good at giving you a sense of
what deep history is and how to apply
evolutionary biology especially with
respect to the changing brain over time
to understand our deep origins now
another book this one's highly technical
very dense this is not for the light of
heart but it's a fantastic book is
incomplete nature by Terrence Deacon now
what Terry does in this book is on he
takes as expertise which is easing the
anthropologist and he studies the
evolutionary develop
of the human brain and how it came into
being and so what he does in this book
is just phenomenal is he very rigorously
shows how dynamic patterns can form to
create goal-directed behavior so we know
that all biological organisms are
goal-directed they try to survive and
they're trying to reproduce and humans
have this really amazing ability to
consciously set goals for ourselves and
be purposeful and so in this book he
explains how those dynamic patterns
emerge this is a book that looks a lot
of complexity and how complexity emerges
in natural systems to explain how the
mind can emerge in a natural system that
is the human organism as it evolves so
it's it's very good book but like I said
not for the faint of heart it's
definitely more of a scholarly work now
in a similar vein of applying complexity
to a human nature in the mind here's one
that's really a lovely book out of
control by Kevin Kelly you see the new
biology of machines social systems in
the economic world Kevin Kelly is the
executive editor of Wired magazine this
was one of the major inspirations for
the matrix movies in the 90s and what
Kevin Kelly does in his book is he
challenges the notion that machine
intelligence artificial intelligence
will be different from human
intelligence by saying that the way that
we will develop artificial intelligence
is through biomimicry as we better
understand how biological systems work
like say the way that an ant navigates
through a space then we improve robotics
we improve machine learning and what we
end up with is this place where you can
no longer separate machine from
biological organism an example of this
in today's context would be twitter
twitter is a technology it's a machine
like a robot but it works by connecting
lots of humans into a large collective
intelligence and the the processing of
Twitter requires human activity as much
as the machine piece of it and really
you can't separate the functionality of
Twitter into human and machine they're
completely blended so that kind of
philosophical thinking
was developed by Kevin Kelly in this
book and it's it's a really good read
for understanding kind of delving into
how complexity and biomimicry shape our
understandings of the mind now getting
into a little bit different space let's
talk for a moment about how cognitive
science can be applied to marketing to
communications to organizing people and
to designing better human systems all
these great applications so here's a
cool book by Seth Godin unleashing the
idea virus in this book he explains a
lot of how cognitive psychology can
inform the way that we design ideas so
that they can spread more easily so you
think about the Occupy movement last
year and how readily the Occupy frame in
the 99 percent frame spread all around
the world they spread like a virus and
so they could be understood in the way
the Seth Godin describes in this book if
you want to understand how ideas spread
to self-organize and propagate
themselves this is a great book to read
similarly is this book right here made
to stick by chip Heath Indiana Heath why
some ideas survive and others die this
is a book for people who are in
marketing you want to develop products
and you want to communicate ideas that
spread really rapidly so what they do is
they combine understandings of best
practices in teaching and also
interesting insights into urban legends
and folklore to show how rumors and
ideas spread and how teachers can get
ideas to stick in the minds of students
and they apply their insights into those
two domains to help us understand how to
design ideas so that they are more
sticky in people's minds similarly
there's another book in that same vein
making meaning how successful business
delivers meaningful customer experiences
this book looks at how to design
experience so that experience is
meaningful satisfying and purposeful for
people and it's an exploration of how
the business world is being redefined
around focus on meaning and experience
so if you want to design the experience
for people and understand how to do that
better this is a great book to read
here's another one that I'm actually I'm
a bit disturbed by in some ways but at
the same time it's very useful the
buying brain by a ke Prati now this book
Lum teaches people how to use the best
insights coming out of brain science to
market products to people better you can
see why I find that to be a little
ethically uncomfortable but at the same
time it's very very insightful if you
are a designer so if you design
communications if you design engagement
strategy this book will give you lots of
practical insights here's another one um
that was written by a person who does
media studies stephen duncombe so dream
reimagining progressive politics in an
age of fantasy this book explores how to
use media and pop culture to engage the
masses more effectively very cool book
another one this is a little different
the logic of failure by deitrick corner
so he's dietrich Dorner is a cognitive
psychologist and what he does in this
book as he explains how people fail to
understand the complexity of systems
they're embedded in and make gross
errors that lead to catastrophic failure
so if you're into design of
sustainability and helping people
transition to a sustainable world this
book will help you understand how it is
that people can misunderstand the
systems that they're in and make gross
errors so they might presume that the
global economy can just grow forever and
not understand the system so those kinds
of gross errors are explained very well
with lots of practical insights in this
book alright so we're getting closer you
can see a we're moving along we've
covered a lot of ground but I'm let me
just share a few more with you so here's
another set of books they get more into
how to understand the mind in a broad
way to really incorporate lots of
insights into whatever it is you're
trying to do including living and happy
and fulfilling life so here's a great
book by Jonathan height the happiness
hypothesis so John height is a social
psychologist to focus on
human morality and what he does in this
book is just lovely is he takes all of
the psychological research that's those
out there at the time of writing and
explains how happiness works and how
psychological resilience works and he
does it through the lens of looking at
ancient approaches to wisdom through
prophets and mystics and great
philosophers and shows how they were
right and how they were wrong based on
what we now know from contemporary
psychology very useful book for
understanding yourself your life your
relationships as well as system design
for culture and society alright so I'm a
couple other ones that are maybe a
little more abstract there's another one
by Ray Gibbs you know you wrote that
embody embodiment cognitive science book
intentions and the experience of meaning
this book explains how human
communication works so if you want to
understand the difference between your
intention and communication and now the
context shapes what it's going to mean
to someone it's kind of a technical
academic book but it really delves into
that in a profound way here's another
one of those books that you've probably
not heard of but is incredibly important
in cognitive science the way we think
conceptual blending in the minds hidden
complexities by ghia Phil Kanye and Mark
Turner this book explains how human
creativity works in a profound way they
have this concept of conceptual blending
which is basically the ability of our
brain to take disparate information and
form new Gestalt form new cogent holes
new completeness a--'s new concepts this
book shows us how new concepts arrived
in our arise in the brain it's one of
those foundational works that is going
to have huge repercussions I see if not
this book at least their body of work as
adding ripple effect effects across many
different disciplines over the next few
decades and funny thing is largely
unknown today so if you want to jump
ahead and make major breakthroughs read
this book and and you'll learn a lot
about how human creativity works there's
another one this is the construction of
meaning error a delayed by a
liechtenstein and Paul slovic this I'm
sorry construction of preference this
book is in the realm of decision
research and it's we can see it's a
large book it's a collection of essays
that explain a human decision-making
works so you can see this one full of
lots of important insights for a lot of
different applications and now I'm just
wrap us up I've got this final set of
books these are a combination of books
that look at how we apply cognitive
science to society at large and also how
we see how some misguided notions of
human nature have come into being and
have kind of gotten stuck there so this
is a philosophical book modern social
imaginaries by social order by Charles
Taylor what he does in this book was
really nice as he explains how mythic
narratives like the Horatio Alger story
of pulling yourself up by your
bootstraps can become what he calls the
social imaginary which is a story that
people imagine into being meaning they
they live it as though it's real and it
changes the culture to change the
society the rent so that it becomes real
if enough people believe in pulling
yourself up by your bootstraps you end
up with a more individualistic society
and so he explains how that works so
that cultural dynamic I here's another
one that's kind of an oldie but goodie
walter Lippmann wrote this book public
opinion this book not a really boring
title but it's fantastic under our way
to understand how propaganda works so
walter Lippmann did a lot of wartime
propaganda during World War one and it
also World War two and he was a
foundational thinker and creating the
field of public relations and this book
explains how basically how the media
manipulates the masses and so if you
want to understand how that works to use
it for good or ill this book is out
there and it's widely read and it's a
it's a very important one to kind of
have a foundational understanding of
where public relations and propaganda
come from here's another one
rationalizing capitalist democracy see
it's by awesome amate this book explains
where that there
rational action comes from so if you've
heard a rational choice theory or this
notion that economics should be based on
maximizing self-interest this book
explains how a small set of think tanks
actually one in particular the RAND
Corporation but also a network around
them developed this theory of decision
making in a context that I was never
actually tested and then one later a
psychologist and behavioral scientists
started studying it they showed that it
was wrong so here's a book that explains
the political agenda and the
institutional framework of the
organizations that benefit if net agenda
to bring the theory of rational action
to the fore and make it the dominant
economic paradigm for the global economy
this book explains how that works here's
another one if you want to understand
broad cultural trends the cultural
creatives this book looks at broad
sociological trends to show how human
human civilization especially in the
developed countries because they look
primarily at the US and Western Europe
although there's some in other countries
as well to show how there's an emerging
new way of being where people are much
more grounded in a sense of meaning and
purpose relationship to nature
relationship to community and now that's
transforming the world so this book will
help you understand the global social
movements that are just exploding on the
seam right now probably an even better
book and then the one that I'm going to
finish with today is this one the
empathic civilization the race to global
consciousness in a world in crisis by
Jeremy Rifkin so this book beautifully
describes how modern understandings of
cognitive science are shaping the way
that we understand the history of
civilization specifically though what
Rifkin explores in this book is how as
societies become more sophisticated with
time they become more complex as they
grow how they increase the capacity for
empathy for the people in those
societies and so he lays out for us a
choice point a place where we can go one
way or the other we're either we lead
ourselves to global economic and
civilization collapse and basically
destroyer
or we develop a capacity for empathy
embedded in our civilization that allows
us to save ourselves and move to a new
level of cultural evolution and this
book is just fantastic his mastery of
economics of history of science of
technology and how innovation works just
phenomenal this book explores all of
that so it's kind of like a culminating
point if you want to bring a lot of
understandings of cognitive science
together in a very relevant discussion
of what's happening the world right now
this is a great book so you know i just
gave you this whirlwind I really through
all this at you because you know anyone
watching this video might pick two or
three of these books and find them very
useful but I found it in the way that
I've approached my understanding of
cognitive science that I haven't been
rounded in a particular discipline I
haven't been as like a guest or linguist
you know or some specific field and you
can see from the sampling of books I
shared here that there's this
convergence of understanding across many
different fields of research and for the
first time ever we really are grappling
with a legitimate understanding of human
nature in the mind and now the question
is what do we do with it now my focus
the thing that I'm most interested in is
helping to design the transition process
how do human beings create the change in
the world to move us toward a
sustainable and just global civilization
and there are lots of ways that that can
work and you can see that in this set of
books you can get a sense of my own
personal journey this is a large
sampling of the books that I've read in
cognitive science probably about half of
the ones that I've read and you can see
how it's informed my thinking by just
what's already here now what I'm really
excited about is to see what you do with
it so take this run with it contact me
if you have any questions about any of
these books or if you want to explore
these ideas further I'm a huge proponent
of open access to information and the
democratization of ideas so I'm just
sharing this with you because I want as
many people as possible to
this stuff but of course if I can be of
service and helping you understand it
better please please let me know and in
the meantime I wish you a happy and
fruitful journey in your own
intellectual development and that I hope
this helps to empower you to be a better
change maker in the world so go forth
and multiply